George F. Johnson Papers
George F. Johnson Papers
- Correspondence
  - Executive correspondence, 1901-1945
    - Chrisfield, H. Edward, 1930-1937; general manager (Box 16)
    - Clarke, Herbert C., 1927-1929; sales (Box 16)
    - Dickson, W. F., 1920-1930; auditor-director
      - 1919-1924, 4 folders (Box 16)
      - 1925-1930, 4 folders (Box 17)
    - Douglas, George M., 1905; insurance agent (Box 17)
    - Endicott, Henry B., 1901-1922; partner of George F. Johnson (Box 17)
      Correspondents include E. P. Bliss, treasurer, Bliss Securities of Maine; Charles Ellixer, president, Crane Buckle Company; Gaston, Snow & Saltonstall, Shawmut Bank of Boston, executors of H. B. Endicott estate; Eliot Spalding, treasurer and partner of H. B. Endicott; H. L. Stone, shoe wholesaler
    - Firth, C. M., 1919-1927; treasurer (Box 17)
    - Hogan, W. J., 1931-1933; auditor (Box 17)
    - Johnson, Charles F., Jr., 1921-1938; nephew of George F. Johnson and vice-president and general manager (Box 17)
    - Johnson, George W., 1921-1936; son of George F. Johnson and president of Endicott-Johnson Corporation (Box 17)
      Correspondence includes a critical letter by labor leader, Henry Stude, Chairman, National Bakers Council, November 22, 1934
    - Johnson, John W., 1915-1930; an advertising man in Georgia (Box 17)
    - Muffley, Joseph F., 1930-1933; sales (Box 17)
    - Neiley, Jewett F., 1922-1925; treasurer (Box 17)
    - Paden, J. M., 1922-1925; treasurer (Box 17)
    - Powell, Clyde, 1943-1945; personnel manager (Box 17)
      Correspondence is in the form of letter-size photographic negatives of letters of appreciation sent from major corporations within the industrial geographical triangle of Virginia, New York and Michigan. In this area Powell had toured over sixty plants to address both shop supervisors about safety practices and industrialists on the topic, "Understanding and Controlling Human Behavior."
    - Spalding, Eliot J., treasurer of the Lestershire Manufacturing Company, Boston; later, partner of Endicott-Johnson and treasurer of the corporation
      - Eliot Spalding-P. V. Byrnes Letter Book, 1912-1913; vice-president, Ontario Pipe Line Company, Hamilton, Ontario (Box 18)
      - General correspondence, 1901-1905; 1906-1927; 2 folders (Box 18)
        Correspondents include J. W. Beggs, sales; William M. Bradley, attorney, Portland, Maine; Louis D. Brandeis, attorney, Boston; Cowing, White & Waite, law firm, New York; W. F. Dickson, auditor; Henry B. Endicott, president of Endicott-Johnson Company; S. Firestone, engineer, Rochester; Herbert C. Freeman, C.P.A., Touche, Niven & Company, New York; W. Gillette, production; John Haley, executor, Endicott estate; Harry L. Johnson, brother of George F. Johnson; Thomas Lynch, deputy commissioner, New York Income Tax Bureau; Maurice E. Page, attorney, Binghamton; Laurence H. Parkhurst, Bond Department, Old Colony Trust Company, Boston; Albert L. Schomp, vice-president, American Bank Note Company, New York; H. L. Stone, wholesale shoe dealer, Stone & Porter, New York. (Where employer and company location have not been indicated, it should be assumed that the correspondents held positions in the Endicott-Johnson firm.)
    - Stanford, Leland, 1922-1934; bookkeeper (Box 18)
    - Swartwood, Howard A., 1928-1935; legal department (Box 18)
    - Miscellaneous, 1922-1935 (Box 18)
    - United States government contracts, 1914-1918 (Box 18)
      Correspondents include the Commissioner of Indian Affairs and the Army and Navy Quartermasters
    - Holiday notices to Endicott-Johnson workers, 1942-1948 (Box 18)
  - Employee correspondence
    - Employee correspondence, 1920-1939 (Box 18)
- Subject files
  - Hospital plans (Box 19)
  - International Business Machine Corporation (Box 19)
  - Labor relations (Box 19)
  - Radio programs (Box 19)
- Articles and speeches
  - Magazine articles by George F. Johnson, typescript and printed, 1920-1936
    - "Thirty years without a strike," System: the magazine of business, 37 no. 1, incomplete, January 1920 (Box 19)
    - "A president's letters to his workers," System: the magazine of business, November 1924; January 1925,; February 1925 (Box 19)
    - "Shall we become a nation of jellyfish?" Colliers, June 20, 1925 (Box 19)
    - "Fewer bosses, more thinkers: our management plan," System: the magazine of business, 49 no. 5, May 1926 (Box 19)
    - "Falling commodity prices are today's problem," Printers' ink, 152 no. 2, July 10, 1930 (Box 19)
    - "Why keep wages secret?" Saturday evening post, November 15, 1930; typescript carbon (Box 19)
    - "Idle rumors", May 7, 1931; privately printed (Box 19)
    - "Your part in life: an address delivered to the members of the Men's Bible Class of Johnson City Church," Primitive Methodist journal, August 1936 (Box 19)
    - "The Endicott-Johnson idea", undated; privately printed (Box 19)
  - Newspaper articles by George F. Johnson
    - Miscellaneous, 1920-1955; Most of Johnson's contributions to daily papers appeared in the Binghamton Sun (Box 19)
  - Magazine articles about George F. Johnson, 1920-1955
    - Paul Clay, "Immigration and prosperity linked: influx of foreign laborers to bring wages and prices down to fair basis," Forbes magazine, September 18, 1920 (Box 19)
    - Peter Newton, "Harmony and prosperity are here," Forbes magazine, 1920; incomplete (Box 19)
    - George Mortimer, "George F. Johnson and his 'square-deal towns'," American magazine, January 1921 (Box 19)
    - Rose C. Feld, "Keep close to your men!" Trained men, November-December 1925 (Box 19)
    - John Kelly, "Mr. George F.: another portrait in the industrial gallery," Rotarian, November 1927 (Box 19)
    - "Rubbing the worker the right way," Advertising & selling, June 13, 1928 (Box 19)
    - "$185,000,000.00 in ten years," American shoemaking, October 9, 1929 (Box 19)
    - Roy Dickinson, "Bigger than balance sheets," Printers' ink, 152 no. 5, July 31, 1930 (Box 19)
    - Rose C. Feld, "An industrial democrat points the way," New York times magazine, June 3, 1934 (Box 19)
    - "With labor troubles the world over...," Boot and shoe recorder, July 28, 1934 (Box 19)
    - Rose C. Feld, "Industrialist who shares his wealth," New York times magazine, August 11, 1935 (Box 19)
    - James E. Hill, "A shoe story," Woman republican, 12 no. 25, September 1935 (Box 19)
    - Frederick Tisdale, "George F.," Reader's digest, June 1937 (Box 19)
    - James S. Gibbons, "Has George F. Johnson found key to industrial problems?" Manufacturers' journal, July 1937 (Box 19)
    - S. J. Woolf, "Honors at eighty for great industrialist," Think, October 1937 (Box 19)
    - U. S. Greene, "Capital, labor and the 'square deal plan'," Kiwanis magazine, February 1938 (Box 19)
    - "George F.--maker of shoes and men," Eagle magazine, February 1938 (Box 19)
    - S. J. Woolf, "Honors at eighty for a pathfinder in industry," New York times magazine, October 10, 1937 (Box 19)
    - "Frank conversations on rebuilding the world," Christian advocate, January 20, 1938 (Box 19)
    - B. C. Forbes, "George F. Johnson: humanizer," Forbes magazine, April 15, 1939 (Box 19)
    - "The homecoming of George F. Johnson," Ogontz mosaic, May 1939 (Box 19)
    - "First jobs," Victorian, March 1940 (Box 19)
    - Mabel Barth Ray, "There's magic in the golden rule," Good business, June 1949 (Box 19)
    - "Half a century of shoemaking", November 29, 1955; unidentified typescript (Box 19)
    - Typescript, chapter of an unidentified work, probably from William O. Inglis, George F. Johnson and his industrial democracy (Box 19)
    - "Hand-to-mouth buying cannot be overcome and should not be attempted," unidentified (Box 19)
  - Magazine articles about Endicott-Johnson, 1924-1967
    - "The valley of fair play," Building trades council, September 1920 (Box 19)
    - Daniel C. O'Neil, "The Endicott-Johnson medical service," Industrial doctor, 1 no. 10, October 1923 (Box 19)
    - "Ambitious industrial service," Nation's health, October 10, 1923 (Box 19)
    - "Helping 16,000 employees keep well," Hospital management, November 1923 (Box 19)
    - Daniel C. O'Neil, "The Endicott-Johnson medical service," Journal of industrial hygiene, January 1924 (Box 19)
    - Daniel C. O'Neil, "Where industrial service becomes community service," Nation's health, January 15, 1924 (Box 19)
    - Eli G. White, "The awakening of a company: the story of Endicott-Johnson Corporation," New York, 1967; pamphlet (Box 19)
    - "Employment by cities", April 1934; unidentified separate (Box 19)
  - Miscellaneous writings
    - Miscellaneous typescript or mimeograph, ca. 1930; titles such as "Control of relief efforts," "Making shoes at the rate of 375 pairs a minute," "Assisting employees," "Turn on the light," "If youth but knew," "The community service shoe," and "Installment buying." (Box 19)
  - Speeches
    - Speeches by George F. Johnson, 1923 (Box 19)
    - Speech about George F. Johnson, by William N. Doak, United States Secretary of Labor, at Binghamton, August 27, 1931 (Box 19)
    - Speech about Johnson City Day, by E. M. Tierney (Box 19)
- Pamphlets, broadsides and posters
  - Advertising pamphlets, Endicott-Johnson, 1910-1924 (Box 19)
    Includes a score of leaflets and large pamphlets with titles such as "Better shoes for men and women too," "The world at play," "Hide to retailer," "Shoes in stock," and "Square deal shoes."
  - Advertising pamphlets, other companies, 1913-1926 (Box 19)
    Includes American Leather Producers, Inc., the J. R. Burns Shoe Company, and United Shoe Machinery Company
  - Pamphlets, Endicott-Johnson, policies and by-laws, 1928-1936 (Box 19)
    Includes "The Endicott-Johnson idea," "The Endicott-Johnson family," "The labor policy of Endicott-Johnson and workers," "An E-J worker's first lesson in the square deal," "The Endicott-Johnson medical service," and the corporation "By-laws."
  - Miscellaneous pamphlets, 1927-1953 (Box 19)
    Includes "Booster week, " and "70 years of mutual respect and confidence," April 18-22, 1927
  - Broadsides
    - Advertising and public relations of the Endicott-Johnson firm, 1921-1936 (Box 19)
    - "The E-J Spirit" (Package 2)
    - "The Old Oaken Desk", of George F. Johnson (Package 2)
  - Posters, 1920-1940 (Tube 1013-1014)
    most are titled To the Workers: and offer inspirational messages or statements of company policy and philosophy
- Financial records
  - Appraisals, 1912-1918 (Box 20)
  - Audits, 1914-1920 (Box 20)
  - Bills & receipts, memorial arch for Endicott-Johnson workers, Johnson City, 1922 (Box 20)
  - Cancelled checks, 1899-1919 (Box 20)
  - Cash books, 1892-1913 (Box 20)
  - Cost accounts: equipment, production and maintenance, 1902-1918 (Box 20)
  - Cost accounts, shoe production, 1925-1931 (Box 20)
  - Income taxes: federal and state, working papers, 1916-1918 (Box 20)
  - Inventories: leased machinery (Box 20)
  - Inventories: merchandise, 1910-1917 (Box 20)
  - Ledger, general, 1892-1914 (Box 20)
  - Liberty Bond sales, 1918 (Box 21)
  - Notebook, financial conditions, 1911-1920 (Box 21)
  - Reports
    - Census of manufacturers, U.S. Dept. of Commerce, 1919 (Box 21)
    - Production, 1907-1918 (Box 21)
    - Profits, 1921-1924 (Box 21)
    - Profits, 1925-1929 (Box 21)
    - Profits, 1930-1934 (Box 21)
    - Profits, 1935-1938 (Box 21)
    - Sales, 1904-1925 (Box 21)
    - Miscellaneous (Box 21)
  - Schedules, inventory reserves, 1918-1919 (Box 22)
  - Shares, stockholders and earnings, 1912-1921 (Box 22)
  - Statements
    - Monthly, 1902-1903 (Box 22)
    - Monthly, 1904-1911 (Box 22)
    - Monthly, 1912-1915 (Box 22)
    - Monthly, 1916-1917 (Box 22)
    - Monthly, 1918 (Box 22)
    - Monthly, 1919 (Box 22)
    - Monthly, 1920 (Box 23)
    - Monthly, 1921-1922 (Box 23)
    - Quarterly, 1913-1920 (Box 23)
    - Semi-annual, 1904-1915 (Box 23)
    - Annual, 1913-1949 (Box 23)
    - Annual, 1950-60 (Box 23)
    - Semi-annual & annual, 1961-66 (Box 23)
    - Annual, comparative, 1897-1918 (Box 23)
  - Statements of condition, 1909-1919 (Box 23)
  - Tax receipts, 1912-1918 (Box 23)
  - Trial balances, profit & loss, 1914-1920 (Box 23)
  - Trial balances, profit & loss, 1920-1924 (Box 23)
  - Trial balances, profit & loss, 1925-1934 (Box 23)
  - Bids & contracts, U.S. government, 1914-1917 (Box 24)
  - Wage schedules, 1904 (Box 24)
  - Miscellaneous (Box 24)
  - Subsidiary companies
    - Endicott Water Works Company, 1911-1920 (Box 24)
    - Endicott-Johnson Realty Company, 1909-1924 (Box 24)
    - First National Bank, Lestershire, 1905-1915 (Box 24)
    - International Shoe Company, 1904-1938 (Box 24)
    - Ontario Pipe Line Company, 1907-1910 (Box 24)
    - Ontario Pipe Line Company, 1911 (Box 24)
    - Ontario Pipe Line Company, 1912-1914 (Box 24)
- Legal documents
  - Articles of incorporation, 1909-1922 (Box 25)
  - By-laws, Endicott-Johnson Realty Company (Box 25)
  - Leases, 1896-1909 (Box 25)
  - Manager contracts, 1902-1907 (Box 25)
  - Manufacturing and utility contracts and sub-contracts, 1901-1919 (Box 25)
  - Partnership and stock agreements, 1907-1934 (Box 25)
  - Power of attorney, 1902-1918 (Box 25)
  - Mortgages, real estate sales, 1899-1936 (Box 25)
  - Right of way license, 1905 (Box 25)
  - Trade marks, 1901-1910 (Box 25)
  - Miscellaneous (Box 25)
- Serial publications and clippings
  - A Magazine, and E-J Workers Review
    - 1919, March-December, 3 folders (Box 26)
    - 1920, January-December, 3 folders (Box 26)
    - 1921, January-April (Box 26)
  - E-J Workers Magazine
    - 1922 Oct.-Dec. (Box 26)
    - 1923, February-May, July, September, December (Box 26)
    - 1924 February-March, June-Sept. (Box 26)
    - 1924 Oct.-Dec. (Box 26)
    - 1925 January-April (Box 26)
    - 1925 May-October (Box 26)
  - Endicott-Johnson Workers Monthly Review
    - April 1933 (Box 26)
  - Fragments
    - Miscellaneous (Box 26)
  - "Endicott-Johnson Workers Daily Page," Binghamton Sun
    - 1928, May-December, 8 folders (Box 27)
    - 1929, January-April, 4 folders (Box 27)
    - 1929, May-December, 8 folders (Box 28)
    - 1930, January-February, 2 folders (Box 28)
    - 1930, March-December, 10 folders (Box 29)
  - Clippings
    - About Henry B. Endicott, 1897 (Box 30)
    - About George F. Johnson, 1914-1923
      - 1924-1927 (Box 30)
      - 1931, August-September (Box 30)
      - 1933 (Box 30)
      - 1934 (Box 30)
      - 1935-1936 (Box 30)
      - 1937-1938 (Box 31)
      - 1939-1947 (Box 31)
    - Obituaries of George F. Johnson, 1948 (Box 31)
    - About Mrs. George F. Johnson, 1927 (Box 31)
    - About the Endicott-Johnson Corporation, 1914-1933 (Box 31)
  - Scrapbooks of newspaper clippings, 1904-1936; 2 vols. and 1 folder (Package 1)
- Memorabilia
  - Awards and decorations, 1928-1938 (Box 32)
  - Blueprints of En-Joie Park clubhouse addition, 1932; Seabreeze Casino; Railroad crossing elimination, 1921; Highway revision, 1919 (Tube 1015)
  - Printed material about Binghamton, New York, 1892 (Box 32)
  - Mementos of celebrations honoring George F. Johnson, 1914-1931 (Box 32)
  - Drawings of George F. Johnson, 1937 (Box 32)
  - Engraving plates, 2 folders (Box 32)
  - Biographical data about Mrs. George F. Johnson (Box 32)
  - Lot maps of Lestershire and the Lester Shoe Company factory, 1888 (Box 32)
  - Mat proofs and printing cuts (Box 32)
  - Petition for a bank in Endicott, 1919 (Box 32)
  - Photographic collages of George F. Johnson with Endicott-Johnson employees, 4 items (Package 2)
  - Photographic portraits, autographed, of Rudy Vallee and Max Schmelling (Box 32)
  - Photographs of Endicott-Johnson factories (Box 32)
  - Photographs of Endicott-Johnson workers (Box 33)
  - Photographs, Johnson family and friends, 1909-1946; 1956; 3 folders (Box 33)
  - Photographs, miscellaneous, 1890-1900 (Box 33)
  - Photographs of sports events, celebrations, and views of Binghamton, N.Y., and vicinity, 1902-1944; 2 folders (Box 34)
  - Printing plates (Box 34)
  - Programs, 1925-1936 (Box 34)
  - Sheet music, 1919 (Box 34)
  - Verse and cartoons (Box 34)
  - Medals, 1919-1950; 10 items, 2 ribbons, 3 boxed medals (Box 35)
  - Seminar Papers, May, 1970; Polf, William "George F. Johnson and his Welfare Capitalism" (Box 35)
- Films and phonotapes
  - Film, 1931; "George F. Johnson is honored: all Binghamton turns out to celebrate 50th anniversary of popular manufacturer in a a mammoth parade"; 16mm, VHS and DVD copies (Box 37)
  - Phonotapes
    - "George F. Johnson funeral", December 1, 1948; 2 reels (Box 36)
    - "Dedication of monument to George F. Johnson", October 14, 1951; 1 reel (Box 36)